{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "While attending a sermon by this leader, reformer Michael Servetus was arrested and later burned at the stake. The Huguenots of France were Protestants who followed the doctrine of this reformer who served as de facto head of the Council of Geneva. This man attacked Roman Catholics and outlined his belief in “predestination” in the work Institutes of the Christian Religion. For ten points, name this Protestant reformer who fled France for Switzerland in 1536.",
      "answer": "John Calvin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lyman Wilbur controversially gave this structure its name. The Mike O'Callaghan- Pat Tillman Memorial Bridge rerouted traffic that once passed over this structure on Highway 93. Tourists can visit this structure by taking Highway 11 for forty minutes southeast of Las Vegas. Building this structure caused Boulder Canyon to be flooded by the newly-created Lake Mead. For ten points, what dam along the Colorado River is named for the president who was in office from 1929 to 1933?",
      "answer": "Hoover Dam"
    },
    {
      "question": "Failed speculation on this commodity from Peru led to the self-proclaimed Emperor Norton losing his fortune. A movement named for “Five Pecks of [this commodity]” began when Zhang Daoling claimed to see a vision in which he was commanded to build a “new state.” Innovations in producing this crop, sometimes grown on terraces, caused the population growth of Song China. For ten points, name this food grown in paddies and often eaten in its grain form.",
      "answer": "Rice"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this decade, Derek Jacobi portrayed a stuttering Roman emperor in the miniseries I, Claudius. Quincy Jones scored a smash-hit ABC miniseries in this decade based on a book about Alex Haley’s ancestry titled Roots. Sixteen Emmy Award nominations were given, with only one winner for Costume Design, to a TV show based in and named for this decade. For ten points, in what decade did the first two Godfather films win Academy Awards for Best Picture?",
      "answer": "1970s 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "One story supporting the plausibility of an early Japanese version of this accomplishment concerns the plight of the Three Kichis [[KEE-chees]]. The Dorset culture accomplished this feat but had dissipated by at least 1500. Another group that accomplished this feat, the Thule [[THOO-lee]], were called skraelings by another group who accomplished this feat and established L’Anse aux Meadows [[lahn-tsoh-meh-DOH]]. For ten points, name this accomplishment whose celebration has been renamed in some states to Indigenous Peoples Day from Columbus Day.",
      "answer": [
        "Discovering the Americas",
        "discovering the New World",
        "descriptive answers indicating new settlement in America",
        "the New World"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these systems known as a \"village\" type originally developed in the town of Chilmark, Massachusetts. That system, which developed on the island of Martha's Vineyard, is now extinct but was used by nearly every resident of the area until the early 20th century. One of these systems which spontaneously arose among students at the Villa Libertad in Managua was first studied by linguist, Judy Shepard-Kegl. Thomas Gallaudet [[gah-low- DET]] created a university, for ten points, to support users of what languages, often used by deaf communities?",
      "answer": [
        "Sign languages",
        "specific sign languages"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A century-long war which was fought over this resource ended when Louis-Hector de Callière [[kah-LYEHR]] negotiated the Great Peace of Montreal. The French-Canadian coureurs des bois [[kor-UHR day-BWAH]] were men who traded these goods with Native Americans. The Embargo Act forced John Jacob Astor to found a company named for this good and to create trading posts in the Pacific Northwest. For ten points, name this good often processed from the pelts of beavers.",
      "answer": [
        "Furs",
        "beaver pelts before mentioned",
        "answers indicating animal skins"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a depiction of this battle, lithographers Currier & Ives sketched the death of Henry Clay, Jr. while he led the 2nd Kentucky Volunteers. During this battle, the Saint Patrick’s Battalion, made up of Spanish-speaking Irish ex-pats, manned heavy batteries that were stormed by the 1st Dragoon regiment. This battle occurred in La Angostura, in the state of Coahuila [[kwah-HWEE-lah]]. For ten points, name this inconclusive battle between sides led by Zachary Taylor and Santa Anna during the Mexican-American War.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Buena Vista",
        "Battle of La Angostura before mentioned 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Music played by lunera [[loo-NEH-rah]] accompanied these people at some events before which these participants were usually massaged with oil. The greatest honor that these people could achieve was receiving a wooden sword known as a Rudis. The Hoplomachus [[hop-loh-MAHK-us]] and Murmillo [[muhr-MIH-loh]] were two specific types of these people who were trained at schools after being bought by a master. Including Spartacus and many rebels in the Third Servile War, for ten points, who were these enslaved competitive fighters of ancient Rome?",
      "answer": "Gladiators"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2016, this politician defeated Loretta Sanchez in one election following Sanchez's controversial remarks about Muslims. During the 2020 Democratic primary, this politician notably attacked Joe Biden for his opposition to bussing policies. Former Georgia Senator David Perdue drew criticism for allegedly intentionally mispronouncing this politician's first name. As a Senator, this politician was preceded in office by Barbara Boxer and succeeded by Alex Padilla. For ten points, name this U.S. vice president.",
      "answer": "Kamala Harris 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2012, this park's Curry Village tent city was linked to a hantavirus outbreak. The Ahwahneechee people were driven out of the region which is now this park after the Mariposa Wars. This park's Fallen Tunnel Tree is a giant sequoia that fell in 1969. Theodore Roosevelt gave federal protection to this park's region at the behest of John Muir [[MURE]]. During a trip to this park, Ansel Adams took iconic photographs of El Capitan and Halfdome. For ten points, name this American national park located in the Sierra Nevada Mountains of eastern California.",
        "answer": "Yosemite National Park"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other park was made a national park with the passage of the California Desert Protection Act. This park is named for the native Yucca brevifolia.",
        "answer": "Joshua Tree National Park"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Condor Legion, a detachment of this organization, was sent to aid Nationalist forces in the Spanish Civil War. Under Albert Kesselring, this organization conducted Operation Retribution, which resulted in the death of over 17 thousand Yugoslav civilians. On Adlertag, or Eagle Day, this organization lost nearly fifty aircraft while attempting to gain superiority over the British Royal Air Force. For ten points, name this military organization, the aerial warfare branch of the Nazi Wehrmacht.",
        "answer": "Luftwaffe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1937, the Luftwaffe contributed to the destruction of this city in Spain, memorialized in a painting by Pablo Picasso.",
        "answer": "Guernica"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1946 Conference in this nation’s capital was coordinated by \"Lucky\" Luciano to coordinate mob policies and discuss collective business interests. The U.S. refused to recognize this nation’s government, which was led by Ramón Grau, after he nullified the Platt Amendment. The explosion of the USS Maine off this nation’s coast led to war between the U.S. and the Kingdom of Spain. The U.S. trained exiled men as paramilitaries to overthrow, for ten points, what nation’s Castro government as part of the Bay of Pigs Incident?",
        "answer": "Republic of Cuba"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The American government supported this Cuban dictator, the predecessor to Fidel Castro, who was overthrown by the 26th of July Movement.",
        "answer": "Fulgencio Batista 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The sparsely populated Chausey [[SHOW-ZEH]] Islands are the southernmost group of islands in this body of water. The two largest territories in this body of water are two semi-independent bailiwicks which claim sovereignty based on the \"constitution\" of King John. The 1120 White Ship disaster occurred during an attempt to cross this body of water. In 1875, Matthew Webb became the first person to swim across this body of water unaided. For ten points, name this seaway which separates France from a namesake island nation.",
        "answer": "English Channel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This largest of the Channel Islands was occupied by Germany during most of World War Two but had a resistance cell led by Norman Le Brocq.",
        "answer": "Bailiwick of Jersey"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person, who got himself intentionally court martialed out of West Point, published a book of poetry with works like “Tamerlane” after a generous donation from his fellow cadets. The 1841 killing of the “Beautiful Cigar Girl” inspired this man's novel \"The Mystery of Marie Rogêt\" [[ROH-ZHEH]] featuring detective C. Auguste Dupin. The tearing down of the historic but derelict Hezekiah House in Boston inspired this writer’s story “The Fall of the House of Usher.” For ten points, name this American author of “The Pit and the Pendulum” and “The Raven.”",
        "answer": "Edgar Allan Poe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "By claiming to be a Whig, Edgar Allan Poe attempted to get a clerical post in this president's bureaucracy but was too drunk to show up to that 1841 meeting.",
        "answer": "John Tyler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Prince Albert loaned his horses to model for a statue of this woman and her daughters now situated on Westminster Bridge. This woman's husband, Prasutagus [[prah- soo-TAY-gus]], willed half of his kingdom to his daughters and half to the emperor. The Roman Empire's gross mistreatment of this woman and her family led her to rebel against Governor Gaius Suetonius Paulinus and lead a tribal army across Britain to burn the city of Londinium. For ten points, name this woman, a modern folk hero and the historical queen of the Celtic Iceni [[eye-SEEN-ee]].",
        "answer": [
          "Boudica or Boadicea",
          "or Boudicea",
          "or Buddug"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Poet Laureate during the reign of Queen Victoria wrote a poem titled \"Boadicea\" as well as a tale of King Arthur titled Idylls of the King.",
        "answer": "Alfred, Lord Tennyson 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two tribes of these people clashed at the Battle of Hingakaka due to an inequitable distribution of kahawai fish. This group, which pursued a \"King Movement\" in the 1850s, used Pā hillforts to defend from intertribal raids during their destructive Musket Wars. William Hobson negotiated the poorly-translated Treaty of Waitangi to give the British Crown dominion over this people’s historic land on North Island. For ten points, name these indigenous people of New Zealand.",
        "answer": "Maori"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Maori are a part of this ethnolinguistic group of seafaring people which includes the natives of Hawaii and Samoa.",
        "answer": "Polynesians"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, an incident in which four police officers were killed by Robert Charles sparked deadly race riots in 1900. In 1873, Sheriff Christopher Columbus Nash orchestrated a massacre of Black militiamen in this state’s Colfax massacre. Homer Plessy intentionally violated this state’s Separate Car Act by sitting in a whites-only car headed to St. Tammany Parish, leading to a landmark U.S. Supreme Court case. For ten points, name this state whose diversity is exemplified by its Creole culture.",
        "answer": "Louisiana"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Plessy v. Ferguson established this legal doctrine justifying segregation, later declared unconstitutional in Brown v. Board of Education.",
        "answer": "Separate but equal"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The War on Terror",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. Defense headquarters building attacked in 2001",
          "answer": "The Pentagon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Al-Qaeda leader who took responsibility for that attack",
          "answer": "Osama bin Laden"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where that man was found and killed during Operation Neptune Spear",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial 2001 act which allowed law enforcement to wiretap domestic phones without a warrant",
          "answer": "USA PATRIOT Act or Uniting and Strengthening America by Providing Appropriate Tools Required to Intercept and Obstruct Terrorism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phrase coined by George W. Bush in 2002 to describe state sponsors of terrorism including Iran, Iraq, and North Korea",
          "answer": "Axis of Evil"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. Navy destroyer that was attacked by a suicide bomber while in Yemen",
          "answer": "USS Cole"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who oversaw coalition forces in Iraq and later pled guilty to leaking confidential information to Paula Broadwell",
          "answer": "David Petraeus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret department created by the DOD to oversee psychological operations",
          "answer": "Office of Strategic Influence"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Fascist Italy",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Dictator, known as \"Il Duce,\" who seize control of Italy in 1925",
          "answer": "Benito Mussolini"
        },
        {
          "question": "Paramilitary wing of the Fascist Party which helped that leader seize power during the March on Rome",
          "answer": [
            "Blackshirts",
            "Camicie Nere",
            "CCNN",
            "squadristi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian king who ordered the arrest of his prime minister in 1943",
          "answer": "Victor Emmanuel III or Vittorio Emanuele III"
        },
        {
          "question": "1939 agreement that created an official alliance between Italy and Germany",
          "answer": [
            "Pact of Steel",
            "Pact of Friendship and Alliance between Germany and Italy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who issued Non abbiamo bisogno to denounce Fascist persecution of the church",
          "answer": "Pope Pius XI"
        },
        {
          "question": "Raid led by Otto Skorzeny to rescue an Italian leader imprisoned at a remote mountain plateau",
          "answer": "Gran Sasso Raid"
        },
        {
          "question": "German puppet state established after the Armistice of Cassibile",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Salo",
            "Italian Socialist Republic",
            "RSI"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "September 1943 uprising against German forces occupying the capital of Campania",
          "answer": [
            "Four Days of Naples",
            "Quattro giornate di Napoli 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Ottoman Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Republic of Turkey which grew out of the Ottoman Empire",
          "answer": "Ankara"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of knights that grew out of a medical institution who stopped the Ottoman conquest of Malta",
          "answer": [
            "Knights Hospitaller",
            "Order of Saint John"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sultan called \"the Magnificent\" who led the empire to its greatest extent",
          "answer": [
            "Suleiman I",
            "Suleiman the Magnificent",
            "Suleiman the Lawgiver"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1526 battle which that ruler won to complete the Ottoman conquest of Hungary",
          "answer": "Battle of Mohács ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who conquered Tunis in 1534, one year after being appointed Grand admiral of the Ottoman navy",
          "answer": [
            "Hayreddin Barbarossa",
            "Hizir Reis",
            "Hizir Hayrettin Pasha"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sultanate founded by slave soldiers in Egypt which was overthrown by the Ottomans in 1517",
          "answer": "Mamluk Sultanate"
        },
        {
          "question": "1522 siege at which the Ottomans expelled Catholic forces from the largest Dodecanese island",
          "answer": "Siege of Rhodes"
        },
        {
          "question": "16th and 17th century period during which the empire was essentially ruled by the wives and mothers of the sultan",
          "answer": "Sultanate of Women or Kadinlar Saltanati 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While jailed in Occitania, this man wrote \"No Man is Imprisoned,\" after which he was moved to Trifels Castle despite Pope Celestine II's threat of excommunication. This ruler was captured by Leopold of Austria for having killed Conrad of Montferrat [[monh-feh-RAH]] before being ransomed by (20 pts)",
        "Emperor Henry VI. This ruler died at Chalus-Chambrol [[shah-LOO shahm-BROHL]] after warring with his former friend and ally, Philip Augustus of France. The co-signer of the Treaty of Jaffa with (10 pts)",
        "Saladin, for ten points, who was this king of England during the Third Crusade?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Richard I or Richard the Lionhearted",
        "or Richard, Coeur de Lion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Future Baseball Commissioner Kennesaw Mountain Landis convicted a participant in this sport, Jack Johnson, for violating the Mann Act by transporting a white woman across state lines. A man who participated in this sport’s “Battle of the Century” with (20 pts)",
        "Joe Louis had earlier refused Adolf Hitler’s personal request to fire his Jewish promoter. Ferdinand Marcos hosted the “Thrilla in (10 pts)",
        "Manila,” a bout in this sport between Joe Frazier and Muhammad Ali. The Marquess of Queensberry established the modern rules of, for ten points, which contact sport?"
      ],
      "answer": "Boxing"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Anita Snook trained this person, and Betty Klenck thought she heard this person ask her husband to take out a suitcase. Gerald Gallagher claimed to have found this person's sextant, and the Gardner hypothesis attempts to explain this person's (20 pts)",
        "fate. Navigator Fred Noonan worked with this person to fly a Lockheed Electra 10E. While flying to Howland Island from Lae [[LAY]], New Guinea, this person (10 pts)",
        "vanished over the Pacific Ocean. For ten points, name this aviation pioneer, the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean."
      ],
      "answer": "Amelia Earhart"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The persecuted Hazaras minority group opposed this group by joining the Northern Alliance led by deposed president Burhanuddin Rabbani. This organization’s leader, Mohammed Omar, ordered the destruction of the giant (20 pts)",
        "Buddha statues of Bamiyan in 2001. This Sunni regime, which succeeded the Mujahideen, combined Pashtun cultural norms with a draconic interpretation of (10 pts)",
        "Sharia [[SHAH-REE-AH]] law. For ten points, name this fundamentalist group which controlled Afghanistan from 1996 until it was overthrown by the 2001 U.S. invasion."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Taliban",
        "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan",
        "IEA 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man attempted to annul his forty-year marriage to Louisa Frederici, falsely claiming that she tried to poison him twice. This man, who sometimes went by the native name Pahaska, served as a (20 pts)",
        "courier on the Pony Express at age fifteen. This man gained his sobriquet at age 22 after defeating William Comstock in a hunting contest while supplying (10 pts)",
        "meat for workers on the Kansas Pacific Railway. For ten points, name this showman who owned a namesake Wild West show which employed the likes of Annie Oakley and Sitting Bull."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Buffalo Bill Cody",
        "Buffalo Bill"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A portion of one of these structures was built in Kicking Horse Pass on the border of Alberta and British Columbia. Construction of one of these structures was led by Sandford Fleming, and the Pacific Scandal involved the building of one of these structures. Navvies [[NAH-vees]] and (*) coolies helped build one of these structures for Canada for which Craigellachie [[kruh-GEH-luh-kee]] was the site of the last (*) spike. The Canadian Pacific forms, for ten points, what type of structure which crosses North America?"
      ],
      "answer": "Transcontinental Railroad"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city's historical coat of arms depicts a white sheep carrying a golden cross with a flag attached. This city contains the longest continuously inhabited executive mansion in the Americas, La Fortaleza [[for-tah-LEH-zah]]. The most populous of this city's eighteen (20 pts)",
        "barrios is Santurce [[san-TUHR-say]]. This city's Castillo San Felipe del Morro successfully repelled a 1595 invasion attempt by Sir Francis Drake and is home to the Spanish-built fortress (10 pts)",
        "Castillo San Cristobal. For ten points, name this capital and largest city of Puerto Rico."
      ],
      "answer": "San Juan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the aftermath of this event, Henry Garnet was killed for refusing to break the confidentiality of confession. Francis Tresham may have sent a letter to William Parker which revealed the plans for this event. The leaders of this event had earlier raided (20 pts)",
        "Warwick Castle, a move that led Richard Walsh to corner them at the Holbeche House. The perpetrators of this event hoped to usher in a Catholic state by putting Elizabeth (10 pts)",
        "Stuart on the throne. James I was targeted in, for ten points, what plot in which Guy Fawkes attempted to blow up the House of Lords?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gunpowder Treason Plot",
        "the Jesuit Treason 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      ]
    }
  ]
}